Register of the Ona Simaite Papers, 1941-1970.
Hoover Institution Archives
Ona Simaite papers,
1941-1970
74075
Simaite, Ona, 1894-1970
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, notes, memorabilia, and photographs, relating to underground aid to the Jewish ghetto inhabitants of Vilnius, Lithuania, during the German occupation, 1941-1944.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1974.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (3 reels).
Access Points
Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945); Jews--Lithuania.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Lithuania.; World War, 1939-1945--Underground movements.; Lithuania.; Lithuania--History--German occupation, 1941-1944.
Biographical Note
1894 Born, Akmene, Lithuania
1941-1944 Librarian and literary critic at Vilna University, involved in underground aid to the Jewish ghettos during the German occupation of Vilnius, Lithuania
1944 Arrested and sentenced to death for aid to Jews, Vilna University officials intervened and she was sent to Dachau and later to a camp in southern France
1953 Arrived in Israel and remained there until death, living with those whom she aided during World War II in Vilnius
1970 Died, Israel
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL, MEMORABILIA, AND MISCELLANEOUS FILE, 1941-1970
  - Scrapbook, 1941-1970 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1956-1970
  - Baltrusaitis, J., 1964 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Baltusis, J., 1965 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Birziskaite-Zymantiene, Marija, 1956 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Churginas, Aleksys, 1966-1969 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Cilvinaite, Marija, 1957, 1962, 1969 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Dainauskas, Jonas, 1959-1970 (Box-folder 1: 7-9)
  - Gudelis, Martynas, 1957-1966 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Kauneckas, Vytautas, 1957-1969 (Box-folder 1: 11-13)
  - Landsbergis, Vytautas, 1968 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Liobyte, Aldona, 1964-1969 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Lukauskaite, Ona, 1969 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Meras, Icchokas, 1960-1967 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Neris (Salemeia) Museum in Kaunas, Lithuania, 1966, 1968 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Students in Vilnius, Lithuania, 1966 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Tumelis, Juozas, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Urbsys, Juozas, 1959-1969 (Box-folder 2: 8-11)
  - Zukas, Vladas, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 2: 12)
- PHOTOGRAPHS (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    22 prints depicting Lithuanian friends and associates of Simaite